A Guide to the Papers of the Page-Barbour and Richard Lecture Committees, [1907]-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Page-Barbour and Richard Lecture Committees [1907]-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-20/23/1.901
This collection consists of ca. 700 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to the library by the Committee through William Harbaugh on 1990 June 21.
Biographical/Historical Information
Committee overseeing the Page-Barbour Foundation and James W. Richard Lectureship established to fund lectures by eminent scholars in the letters and sciences, and in comparative history and the Christian religion respectively.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of topical and speaker files. The former contains committee correspondence; membership lists; nominations, invitations and regrets, University Press of Virginia royalty statements; requests for co-sponsored lectures and special lectures; and general information on the history of the lectureships.
Topical files also contain correspondence and memoranda re legal problems originating in the publication copyrights and from the strict provisions in the will establishing the Richard lectures.
Speaker files contain correspondence, publicity, schedules, finances and other material pertaining to speakers Asa Briggs, John Hope Franklin, Peter Gay, Jacob Neusner, Jaroslav Pelikan, Jean Starobinski, George Steiner, Thomas F. Torrance, and Clifford Truesdell.
Contents List
- Series I: Topical Files
  - Jenny Clay/Leo Strauss [1987-1988] (Box 1)
  - Committee Memberships, Etc. 1979-1986] (Box 1)
  - Declinations [1979-1984] (Box 1)
  - Small Grants 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Invitations to Lecturers (2 folders) 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Single Lectures1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Special Lectures(2 folders) 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Legal Definition [1907-1987] (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous [1984-1985] (Box 1)
  - Nominations Pending [1981-1983] (Box 1)
  - Notices of Solicitations, Meetings, Etc. [1979-1985] (Box 1)
  - Historical Terms of Page-Barbour Foundation[1983-1984] (Box 1)
  - Small Page-Barbour Grants1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Page-Barbour Lecture Committee [1975-1979] (Box 1)
  - Page-Barbour/Richard Lectures--General (2 folders) 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Suggestions for Possible Future Page-Barbour/Richard Lectures[1987-1988] (Box 1)
  - University Press Royalty Statements for Page-Barbour/Richard Lectures[1970-1984] (Box 2)
  - Page-Barbour/Richard Lectures--Useful and Useless General Information [1986-1987] (Box 2)
  - Page-Barbour/Richard Reports [1973-1985] (Box 2)
  - Speakers [1963-1979] (Box 2)
  - Terms [1970-1979] (Box 2)
- Series II: Speaker Files
  - Asa, Lord Briggs 1983 (Box 2)
  - Bertram Davis [1986] (Box 2)
  - John Hope Franklin (2 folders) [1977]-1981 (Box 2)
  - Peter Gay [1987-1988] (Box 2)
  - Nicholas L.A. Lash n.d. (Box 2)
  - Jacob Neusner 1982 Spring (Box 2)
  - Jaroslav Pelikan 1984 (Box 2)
  - Jean Starobinski 1980 Jan (Box 2)
  - George Steiner [1987] (Box 2)
  - T.F. Torrance [1978] (Box 2)
  - Clifford Truesdell 1985 Sep (Box 2)
  - Bernard Williams 1983 Apr (Box 2)